Guide to the George Trumbull Ladd Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
George Trumbull Ladd papers
1848-1922
MS 1371
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8.75
(16 boxes)
The collection includes correspondence pertaining to George Trumbull Ladd's professional life and international travels, particularly to East Asia and southern Europe; reprints of articles; oversize photographs of Ladd and his wife with dignitaries and others in Japan and Korea; a syllabus of Ladd's lectures on philosophy at Yale University; and some letters of Frances Ladd, George Trumbull Ladd's second wife.
Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Ladd, 1931. Gift of Elizabeth Wadhams Lawrence Trust, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The first accession consists of two letters by George Trumbull Ladd to unidentified recipients, and reprints of more than eighty articles and reviews, bound in four volumes.
The second accession contains late 19th and early 20th century correspondence pertaining to George Trumbull Ladd's international travels, particularly to East Asia and southern Europe; oversize photographs of Ladd and his wife with dignitaries and others in Japan and Korea; a syllabus of Ladd's lectures on philosophy at Yale University; and some letters of Frances Ladd, George Trumbull Ladd's second wife.
Biographical / Historical
George Trumbull Ladd, psychologist, philosopher, and theologian, was born on January 19, 1842 in Painesville, Ohio. In 1864 he graduated from Western Reserve College and in 1869 from Andover Theological Seminary. Ladd was a minister from 1869-1879 when he accepted the chair of philosophy at Bowdoin College. He moved to New Haven in 1881 and for forty years was associated with Yale University. In 1892 Ladd and others founded the American Psychological Association and served as its second president. He frequently traveled to Japan, lecturing on philosophy. Ladd died on August 8, 1921.
Arrangement
The material is arranged by accession.
Custodial History
The volumes were given to the Yale Library by Mrs. Ladd in 1931, and were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives from Sterling Memorial Library stacks. Once at Manuscripts and Archives, the letters were originally in the Miscellaneous Manuscripts and Yale Miscellaneous Manuscripts collections.
Psychology; Religion -- Philosophy; Ladd, George Trumbull, 1842-1921
- Inventory, .5; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged by record type.
  Scope and Contents
  This accession includes two letters by George Trumbull Ladd to incompletely identified recipients, and reprints of more than eighty articles and reviews, bound in four volumes. In a 1903 letter to "Professor Helder", Ladd describes his past and projected work in the field of philosophy of religion. In an undated letter to "Dr. Bacon"-probably either Benjamin Wisner Bacon or his father, Leonard Woolsey Bacon-he discusses the speed of nervous impulses, and speaks of the work of Edward Wheeler Scripture at the Yale psychological laboratory.
  - Correspondence, 1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Essays: 4 bound volumes of printed matter, Circa 1874-1916 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 3)
- Additional material, 1848-1922; Accession 2016-M-0068; 8.25; (15 boxes)
  This accession contains late 19th and early 20th century correspondence pertaining to George Trumbull Ladd's international travels, particularly to East Asia and southern Europe; oversize photographs of Ladd and his wife with dignitaries and others in Japan and Korea; a syllabus of Ladd's lectures on philosophy at Yale University; and some letters of Frances Ladd, George Trumbull Ladd's second wife.
  The accession is arranged in three groupings: correspondence, photographs, and teaching materials.
  - Correspondence
    - 1856-1859 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1864-1869 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - 1869 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1877-1878 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1879 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1879-1881 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1882-1889 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1883 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1886-1888 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1889 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1890 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1891 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1892 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1893 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1895-1897 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1896 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
    - 1898-1900 (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - 1901 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1904 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1906 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1907 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1908 (Box 4, Folder 7, Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1912 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1917 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1918 (Box 5, Item 4)
    - 1919-01-1919-07 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1920-01-1920-06 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
    - 1920-07-1920-12 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Appeals from unknowns, 1902-1909 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Articles, 1876-1879 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Barge, B. F., 1899-1906 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Benevolences of the Edinburgh Church, 1870-1871 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Books, 1883-1909 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Call to Yale, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Camp Chase, 1862 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Divinity School, 1882-1883 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
    - Doctrine of Sacred Scripture, 1878-1883 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Doshisha controversy, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Doshisha affair, 1897-1898 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Edinburgh and Milwaukee, western trip, 1871-1892 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Family, 1848-1872 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Family and friends, 1863-1869 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Family and friends, 1869-1870 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Family and friends, 1908-1909 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - First letters to Neelie, 1866-1869 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Fishing trip, 1865 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Friends, 1861-1864 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Friends, 1879-1880 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Friendship, 1884 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Health breaks down and two-day fishing trip, 1868 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Invitation as guest of honor to Columbian Exhibition, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Invitations, 1899-1900 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Japanese correspondence, 1910-1916 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Japanese passport, 1892 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Kansas City letters, 1866-1869 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Ladd, Frances and Ladd, Elizabeth, 1900 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Letters from others during trip, 1892 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Letters from house during trip, 1892 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
    - Milwaukee letters, 1875-1879 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Minneapolis house, 1886-1899 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1886-1909 (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
      - 1893-1894, 1898, 1898 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - 1894, 1903, 1903 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - 1897-1911 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - 1898-1899 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - 1899-1906 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - 1900 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Neelie's death, 1893 (Box 10, Folder 5-7)
    - Personal, 1871-1879 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
    - Princeton sesquicentennial, 1896 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Seminary and other friends, 1865-1870 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - St. Louis Exposition, 1904-1905 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Testimonies as to work done in Korea and Japan, 1908 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Trip to Japan
      - 1906 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - 1907 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Typed duplicates, 1906-1907 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
    - University celebrations, 1896-1901 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - University letters, 1895-1908 (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
    - Williams, Elizabeth (mother), 1860-1864 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - Photographs
    - Ladd, George and Frances, Undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Memorial book, Undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Family photograph of Mr. and Mrs. Ladd with 7 others, Wakayama, Japan, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Group photograph in schoolyard with Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Tokyo, Japan, Undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Group photograph of men in western attire with Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Group photograph with Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Group photograph with women in traditional attire and Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Korea, 1907? (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Ladd monument ceremony, Soijiji Temple, Tsurumi, Japan, 1922 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Ladd monument ceremony with assembled dignitaries, 1922 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Large assemblage of people with Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Kyoto, Japan, Undated (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Photograph of George Trumbull Ladd and Mrs. Ladd with extended Japanese family, Undated (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Photograph of Mrs. Ladd with Korean women and American girls, Seoul, Korea, 1907? (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Portrait of George Trumbull Ladd, Tokyo, Japan, Undated (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Studio portrait of man in military uniform, Undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Unidentified large group with Mr. and Mrs. Ladd, Undated (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Yale Bicentennial including George Trumbull and Mrs. Ladd, Mrs. George Stevens, New Haven, 1901 (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Teaching materials
    - Japanese flower arrangements, Undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Syllabus of lectures on philosophy material, Undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - "Westward to the Far East: A Guide to the Principal Cities in China and Japan" booklet, 1891 (Box 13, Folder 4)